Guide to the Christopher Phillips Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- November 1982 - February 1984, London: Fleet Street and Orthodox Judaism, Series XI
  - Photograph (photocopy) of Tito from around this time; two photographs (photocopies) of him from September 1994, when he first moved to San Francisco, 1983, 1994 (Box 64, Folder 76)
  - 1983 taxes, and receipts, which give a good idea of day-to-day doings, 1983 January-December (Box 64, Folder 77)
  - Appointment book for my last weeks in London, 1984 January-February (Box 64, Folder 78)
  - Letters overseas to and from me, 1984 January (Box 64, Folder 79)
  - My life [on January 5, I left my apartment in Chelsea to live with an Orthodox family in Golders Green, where I remained until leaving for Israel on February 13]: includes letters from Tito in Amsterdam, 1984 January (Box 64, Folder 80)
  - List of my files as they were being packed in tea chests for shipping from London to Mary Lindsay in Mount Vernon, New York, for safekeeping [and later shipped to Israel, then back to New York in 1991, and presently in this archive], 1984 January (Box 64, Folder 81)
  - My financial logistics: five-page memo to my friend Stephen Breimer in Los Angeles, who would pay all my bills and handle all my affairs as I headed off into the unknown at yeshiva. It explains my bank accounts, credit cards, health insurance, etc., and shows the kind of remote-control living I had to do on the road in the days before fax and e-mail; there is a similar memo for 1981 written in Hong Kong prior to my wanderings, 1984 January (Box 64, Folder 82)
  - Photograph (photocopy) of me with Rabbi Joseph Freilich at 1:30 a.m., in his home in Golders Green [we would often stay up very late talking], 1984 January 3 (Box 64, Folder 83)
  - Visit to Gateshead [near Newcastle] a yeshiva town called "the last shtetl in Europe": relics and ephemera include short photocopy of writings by the famous Gateshead figure Rebbitzen Zipa Lopian ["Auntie Zipa"] and a note by me about her; short letter from me to Rav Mattisyahu Salomon, the mashgiach [spiritual director] of Gateshead Yeshiva, after my meeting with him; an account of the trip, with photograph, written for Rabbi Joseph Freilich's yeshiva magazine [see also "Gallery of photographs" in this series for views of this trip], 1984 January 18-22 (Box 64, Folder 84)
  - Gay: program for a London performance of Hello, Dolly! starring Danny LaRue in the title role, in drag; item from Private Eye magazine; postcard from gallery exhibition showing a leather-clad male Venus de Milo, 1984 January (Box 64, Folder 85)
  - Final days in London: includes purchase of some small antiquities and my visit to the British Museum to have them authenticated, 1984 February 1-13 (Box 64, Folder 86)
  - Atmospheric ephemera: amusing envelopes and things to write letters on, interesting things to enclose in letters, and other odd bits. [This slim file is a representative of the many such files I have always kept and which would have totaled almost a carton]; also a few cartoons and other bits and pieces, 1982-1984 (Box 64, Folder 87)
  - Royal ephemera and clippings: includes material about Prince Edward and the infant Prince William, 1982-83 (Box 65, Folder 88)
  - Thatcherite Yuppiedom: two ephemeral paperback humor books that capture the spirit of the period [neither are in Yale Library catalogue]: The Official Sloane Ranger Handbook and The Complete Naff Guide [see also The Young Fogey Handbook in Series XIII], 1982, 1983 (Box 65, Folder 89)
  - Jewish Studies, non-Orthodox: West London Synagogue [British Reform, equivalent of U.S. Conservative], notes taken by me of lectures by a visiting rabbi, Harold Saperstein [Lynbrook, Long Island, U.S.A.], and of one by Rabbi Hugo Gryn, the famous rabbi of West London Synagogue, 1983 January-1984 February (Box 65, Folder 90)
  - Jewish Studies: commentaries on the weekly Torah portion that I saved, from the Union of American Hebrew Congregations Torah edition: on some pages I have written personal comments or commentary I heard from rabbis, 1983 (Box 65, Folder 91)
  - Baal Tshuvah Movement: notes taken by me in lectures by Rabbi Joseph Freilich, London, including much that I wrote down verbatim; also includes occasional lectures by others at Rabbi Freilich's London Jewish Academy, Golders Green, 1983 January-1984 February (Box 65, Folder 92-94)
  - Baal Tshuvah Movement: envelopes that contained original cassettes; written explanation of the printed notation system., 1983 May-1984 January (Box 65, Folder 95-97)
    General
    The recording speed is slightly off on some of these, making the voice sound too high. See corrected cassette for pitch correction.
    - Corrected cassette (original): this is the proper pitch level, 1 (Box 151)
    - Original cassette of Torah chanting, 1984 January 17; 1 (Box 152)
    - Original cassettes of lectures by Rabbi Joseph Freilich, London
      - 1983 August 25, 1 (Box 153)
        - Use copy, 1 (Box 153U)
      - Hillel House, London, 1983 November 3; 1 (Box 154)
      - Jacob and Esau; Jews and Rest of the World, 1983 November 17; 1 (Box 155)
      - "Nine Days", 1983; 1 (Box 156)
      - 1983 May 26, 1 (Box 157)
      - Korach and Margaret Thatcher, 1983 June 9; 1 (Box 158)
      - Parshas "Chukas", 1983 June 16; 1 (Box 158A)
        - Use copy, 2 (Box 158AUa–158AUb)
      - Parshas "Balak", 1983 June 23; 1 (Box 159)
      - 1983 August 30, 1 (Box 160)
      - Last lecture before Yom Kippur, 1983 September 15; 1 (Box 161)
      - Joseph and Potifar's wife, 1983 December 1; 1 (Box 162)
      - 1984 January 26, 1 (Box 163)
      - Parshas "Pinchas", 1983 June 30; 1 (Box 164)
      - 1983 July 12, 1 (Box 165)
      - Elul #3 (first tape), 1983 August 23; 1 (Box 166)
      - Elul #3 (tape #2), 1983 August 23; 1 (Box 167)
      - To 75 end/last before Yom Kippur, 1983 September 15; 1 (Box 168)
      - Hillel House, Thursday, 1983 October 20; 1 (Box 169)
      - Hillel House, V'hage Sarah, 1983 October 27; 1 (Box 170)
      - Yacov and Esau; Jews and Rest of World, 1983 November 17; 1 (Box 171)
  - Avromi Freilich [born 1971]: original cassette of him singing the Orthodox Grace After Meals in Hebrew. Avromi, who is one of Rabbi Joseph Freilich's sons, later became a prominent London cantor; this is probably his first recording, 1983 September
    - Envelope (Box 65, Folder 98)
    - Recording, 1 (Box 172)
- February 1984 - September 1987, Jerusalem: Yeshiva Life and a Start as a Book Publisher, Series XII
  -- February 13-26, 1984, I traveled from London to Israel, via Paris, Venice, and Greece, where I caught a boat for Haifa. By this time I was living as a fully Orthodox Jew.
  -- On February 26, 1984, I arrived in Jerusalem.
  -- Also in February 1984, in my first couple of days in Jerusalem, I ran into my brother Adam Phillips, who had just arrived and was starting to study in a Baal Tshuvah (Newly Orthodox) yeshiva called Aish Hatorah, in the Old City. He stayed in Israel until spring 1986.
  -- February 1984 to January 1985, I lived at Ohr Somayach, a Baal Tshuvah yeshiva in the Ma'alot Dafna section of Jerusalem, near the old "Green Line." I was a full-time student at this so-called "back-hat" English-speaking yeshiva that is part of the non-Hassidic, Lithuanian [in Yiddish: Litvak] tradition.
  -- January 1985, I moved from the yeshiva to a little courtyard house, circa 1900, in the Nachla'ot neighborhood of Jerusalem, which I first rented and later bought. My brother Adam Phillips got an apartment nearby.
  -- May 19 to September 8, 1985, I was in the United States, mostly staying in my friend Stephen Breimer's late mother's apartment on the newly gay Upper West Side of New York. But I also spent time in San Francisco, Los Angeles and our family house on Cape Cod. On my way to the States, I spent three weeks in Europe --first visiting Jerome Gold (formerly Crickett Bon Bon of the Gay Community Services Center and Highland Park Collective) and Juliet Man Ray (the artist's widow) in France, then joining my brother David F. Phillips in Spain. I was living a totally Orthodox life on this trip. A visual image from that summer says it all: me, in yarmulke and Orthodox fringes, sitting on the New York subway laughing and gleefully underlining juicy passages in my copy of Diana Vreeland's autobiography.
  -- Fall 1985, I began the process of becoming an immigrant to Israel and enrolled in a Hebrew-language school for immigrants, called an Ulpan; many of my classmates were newly arrived Ethiopians.
  -- January 1986, I started to develop book ideas that eventually grew into a book packaging business, meaning that I produced illustrated books under contract with publishers. This was the beginning of Phillips & Company Books, which brought me back to London to live in September 1987. Also at this time I was doing editing projects for a religious publishing house in Jerusalem, Targum Press, which was just starting up.
  -- March 2-13, 1986, I was in Paris to visit Jerome Gold and to work with Man Ray's widow, Juliet Man Ray, on a book; Jerry was her administrator and personal assistant. The original idea was a book about Juliet to be produced by the late John Calmann's book packaging firm in London, with assistance from me. This eventually became a new illustrated edition Self Portrait, Man Ray's autobiography, the first title produced by my own company. I spent a great deal of time in Man Ray's studio and darkroom on the Rue Férou in Paris, which had not been changed at all since his death, in 1976.
  -- Winter 1985-86, I broke with Orthodox Judaism and stopped living according to Jewish law. I remained in Israel, however, and was discreet about this change when I was in Jerusalem. Little by little, I left the Orthodox milieu and rejoined my old ambitions in the wider world, especially publishing. I did the same thing in my spiritual life: since I remained convinced that Orthodoxy was the authentic version of Judaism, I could not go back to the Conservative path. So my own personal approach to God and prayer, which had been strong since earliest childhood, was allowed to flourish again, away from the rules and regulations of religion.
  -- Spring 1986, my brother Adam Phillips left Jerusalem.
  -- September 1986, when I was visiting Amsterdam, my friend Tito (an important involvement starting in 1983) was diagnosed with cancer. From September 1986 until summer 1987 I made constant visits to Amsterdam to see him during his (successful) treatment, at least once a month, often more.
  -- The years 1986 and 1987 saw constant overseas travel, sometimes more than once a month. In addition to the United States, I shuttled back and forth to Paris and London, where I was producing the Man Ray Self Portrait (my designer was in London, but the Man Ray material was in Paris). All the while I was making my trips to Amsterdam to see Tito, and even tried to get one Targum Press book designed there.
  -- December 1986, I had my first Phillips & Company Books sales meeting with Little, Brown, in Boston. They bought the Man Ray Self Portrait project, to be published fall 1988. With my first deal in hand, I had a real company.
  -- April 1987, I attended a course on book production in England. This was urgently needed since I had a contract for producing a book but not the slightest idea how to do it.
  -- Summer 1987, I was on the road without a break, from June 2 to August 17, producing the Man Ray book in cheap hotel rooms and friends' apartments.
  -- On September 8, 1987, I moved back to London from Jerusalem to try my hand at being an international book publisher.
  -- Life in Israel, 1984-87, a peaceful time in Jewish-Arab relations.
  -- Immigrant absorption in Israel, including a government language school, called an Ulpan.
  -- Yeshiva life in Israel.
  -- The so-called "Ultra-Orthodox" world in Israel (called in Hebrew "Haredi": this is different from Hassidic).
  -- I was doing quite a bit of devotional writing at this period (reflected in the diaries as well as these folders).
  -- The Baal Tshuvah (Newly Orthodox) world, showing how yeshivas and rabbis molded Westernized young men and women into Orthodox Jews; includes notes and cassettes from lectures and classes. There is a lot of material from Ohr Somayach yeshiva.
  -- How a Baal Tshuvah broke with Orthodox Judaism.
  -- Jerusalem: the Nachla'ot neighborhood of alleyways alongside the central fruit and vegetable market. It is now a chic artists' quarter, but then it was an undiscovered poor neighborhood, the home of Orthodox Middle Eastern Jews.
  -- Gay Community Services Center and Highland Park Collective, Los Angeles: renewed contact with Jerome Gold (previously Crickett Bon Bon), who was then living in Paris as the personal assistant to Man Ray's widow, Juliet Man Ray.
  -- Visits with Juliet Man Ray in Paris and to Man Ray's studio, which was untouched since his death in 1976.
  -- The start of my "book packaging" business, which meant developing and producing book projects under contract from publishers; this business caused me to move back to London in September 1987.
  -- Book publishing and publishers in London and U.S.A.
  -- The last years of book production under the old technology, before computers took over; included are examples, in things I was writing, of how the old "cut-and-paste" editing system worked, before word processing.
  -- The start-up of the Targum Press, an English-language religious book publishing house in Jerusalem.
  -- The London property market, 1986-87: rentals and prices.
  -- Travels in France, Spain, Britain and U.S.A. while keeping Orthodox Jewish laws.
  -- Life in Amsterdam in its filthy, druggy nadir of the mid-1980's.
  -- Francisco Franco: a piece of ephemeral fan memorabilia still being sold on the streets of Madrid in 1985.
  -- My gradual transformation from a small view of life, centered on the inward-looking worlds of Israel and the yeshiva, to my customary wide-screen view as I traveled and started launching myself in a glamorous-sounding international business.
  -- An extreme version of running before I could walk: starting a book publishing company without ever having set foot inside a book publishing house. Having no any idea how a book was produced, I had to learn along the way.
  -- Gay files (9) include material from Israel, especially the early days of the Israeli gay rights movement (including material from the Society for the Protection of Individual Rights, in Hebrew); also material from Britain, France, U.S.A., Greece, Korea and Taiwan.
  1) Names: During this period, I was known in Israel under my Hebrew name, Chaim Phillips, though many official documents continue to say Christopher.
  2) The name of the yeshiva where I was studying is Ohr Somayach. In Hebrew it is called Yeshivat Ohr Somayach (note the final "t," which is there for grammatical reasons), so in writing about it in English I have called it Ohr Somayach yeshiva, with a lower-case "y."
  3) The plural of the noun Baal Tshuvah, referring to Newly Orthodox individuals, is Baalei Tshuvah. I have avoided this usage, since it might be unfamiliar.
  4) Materials relating to classes and lectures at Ohr Somayach yeshiva and other Baal Tshuvah institutions are grouped together at the end of the series. The theme of Baal Tshuvah life runs throughout this series and the London 1982-84 Series as well. While my lecture notes are in English, many of the words and phrases are in Hebrew, Aramaic or Yiddish, all using the Hebrew alphabet.
  5) Materials relating to specific book projects are grouped together after the chronological files. Man Ray Self Portrait material appears in Series XIII, as does material relating to his widow, Juliet Man Ray.
  6) Dates: I normally used the British dating system, day/month/year, which is customary in Israel and that I had been used to since Hong Kong and London. Sometimes, though, I do it the American way.
  7) Financial data and receipts for 1987, and for Man Ray-related activities in 1986 and 1987, are found in Series XIII.
  - Gallery of photographs (photocopies) from the period, 1984-1987 (Box 66, Folder 1)
  - Relevant pages from my passport covering this period [photocopies: the original is in Series XI], 1984-1987 (Box 66, Folder 2)
  - "Things Not to Miss in Israel": a memo I wrote in 1995 for my Taiwan friend Ursula Richter [who first appears in Series VII] mentioning many of my favorite haunts; five pages, typewritten, 1984-1987 (Box 66, Folder 3)
  - Ephemera, Israel: includes interesting graphics and relics that I found along the way, 1984-1987 (Box 66, Folder 4)
  - Gay, Israel: card for Jerusalem gay bath house, in the historic Orthodox Bukharian Quarter, near the yeshiva; an aerial view, annotated by me, of the cruising park in Jerusalem, Independence Park [in Hebrew: Gan haAtzma'ut], 1984-1985 (Box 66, Folder 5)
  - A representative of the many, many folders full of cards, stationery and interesting enclosures that I have always kept; altogether they would probably fill a carton. [This actual folder is an original document wallet I used at this period, with foreign exchange rates glued in for the week of 3/16/84. This document wallet might have been started in London in January 1984, when I moved to Golders Green, and was definitely used by me when I lived at the yeshiva. The label, written by me in Chinese, says, "Letter-Paper and Envelopes"], 1984-1987 (Box 66, Folder 6)
  - The money that I lived on: stubs for American Express travelers checks, which I would buy at American Express in Jerusalem with a U.S. money-market check at the rate of about $1,000 a month [the envelope, with words in Gaelic, is from the Irish telephone company, a relic of my fall 1983 Dublin trip], 1984-1987 (Box 66, Folder 7)
  - My brother David F. Phillips' envelopes, which he used for his letters to me: sort of works of art, with old stamps, 1984 (Box 66, Folder 8)
  - The journey from London to Jerusalem [via Paris, Venice, Greece, and boat to Haifa]: documents and ephemera. Includes detailed itinerary; letter to Jim Ito in Los Angeles written from Greece, 1984 February 13-26 (Box 66, Folder 9)
  - Gay, Greece, Italy and Israel: card from bath house in Athens; notes I copied from a book listing possible gay venues along the way, including Israel, 1984 February (Box 66, Folder 10)
  - Letter from me to Rabbi Joseph Freilich, my Orthodox rabbi in London, describing my journey to Israel and my first days there: four typewritten pages [it gives a good idea of my spiritual goals and my way of thinking at the time], 1984 February (Box 66, Folder 11)
  - My calendar, 1984 February-May (Box 66, Folder 12)
  - Letters overseas to and from me: includes substantial letters written by me to a London friend about yeshiva life and two notes from Rabbi David J. Seligson, my childhood rabbi from Central Synagogue, New York [it was hard to find a photocopier when I was living at the yeshiva, so I sometimes just made lists of letters and cards sent], 1984 February-May (Box 66, Folder 13)
  - Letter from me to Rabbi Joseph Freilich in London describing my life at Ohr Somayach yeshiva: four typewritten pages, 1984 February-March (Box 66, Folder 14)
  - My life: includes first days in Israel and life at the yeshiva; also my practice rifle targets from Citizens Patrol training, 1984 February-May (Box 66, Folder 15-16)
  - Three photographs (photocopies) from Ohr Somayach yeshiva: the main study hall [Bais HaMedresh]; exterior shot; my desk in the Bais HaMedresh, showing the books I used most often and kept close at hand, 1984-1986 (Box 67, Folder 17)
  - Photocopies of the pages I studied in the Talmud, Section Sukkah, with my notes written in, and vocabulary sheets provided by Ohr Somayach; Mishna texts into which I bound interleaved blank sheets on which to make notes, 1984 March-July (Box 67, Folder 18)
  - Prayers I wrote for my brother Adam Phillips in a pocket-sized "prayer diary" that I made for him. This gives a very good idea of my prayer life at the time, and later, up to the present. It shows the best of me, 1984 April 2 (Box 67, Folder 19)
  - Original cassette made to teach me the singing of the traditional Jewish "Seven Wedding Blessings" ["Sheva Brochos"] in Hebrew: I was often called upon to sing one of these blessings at friends' weddings, 1984 May 22
    - Envelope and note (Box 67, Folder 20)
    - Recording, 1 (Box 67A)
  - My calendar: shows visits of J. Kelley Younger, Architectural Digest friend, June 10-18; Stephen Breimer, August 20-31, including our trip to Egypt; and hints of Tito's July-August stay at the yeshiva, 1984 June-August (Box 67, Folder 21)
  - Letters overseas to and from me [I found a photocopier!], 1984 June-August (Box 67, Folder 22-23)
  - My life: includes some Israeli election flyers and brochure for a new Orthodox West Bank settlement; also, my August trip to the Alsace and Luxembourg with Jerome Gold [previously Crickett Bon Bon of the Gay Community Services Center and Highland Park Collective], including photograph (photocopy); my trip to Egypt with Stephen Breimer, including photograph (photocopy), 1984 June-August (Box 67, Folder 24)
  - Lament [called in Hebrew a Kina] written by me for the Jewish fast of Tisha b'Av at the Western Wall [prose poem, in English, three handwritten pages], 1984 August 7 (Box 67, Folder 25)
  - My calendar, 1984 September-December (Box 67, Folder 26)
  - Letters overseas to and from me, 1984 September-December (Box 67, Folder 27-28)
  - My life [except London, October-November]: in late December I started house hunting and found a small circa-1900 house in the Nachla'ot neighborhood of Jerusalem, to which I moved in January, 1984 September-December (Box 68, Folder 29)
  - Notes on the funeral of the father of Rabbi Budlander of Ohr Somayach yeshiva, including my recollections of the eulogy he gave [father and son were both Newly Orthodox]: two pages, handwritten by me, 1984 September 16 (Box 68, Folder 30)
  - Prose poem written by me after Slichot, the early-morning penitential prayers in the days leading up to Rosh Hashanah [two handwritten pages, in English], 1984 September 23 (Box 68, Folder 31)
  - England: material from my trip to London for the bar mitzvah of Avromi Freilich, a son of Rabbi Joseph Freilich who is now a prominent cantor in London [see also a cassette made by him in Series XI]; also, a weekend in the Orthodox yeshiva town of Gateshead, near Newcastle [this file is in the original document wallet I carried on the trip], 1984 October 23-November 15 (Box 68, Folder 32)
  - Gay, Britain: gay guide, with long article about gay Edinburgh, from the British newspaper Gay Times; my written description of a visit to the fancy Napoleon Club in Mayfair, London; catalogue cover and flyleaf from Glyn Philpot painting exhibition at National Portrait Gallery, which I visited on this trip [Gay researchers, note! Glyn Philpot is important and fascinating], 1984 October-November (Box 68, Folder 33)
  - New York Post parody issue: I am not sure how or why I got this, but I think it was famous at the time, 1984 November (Box 68, Folder 34)
  - 1984 Taxes, and receipts, which are a good record of my day-to-day doings, 1984 January-December (Box 68, Folder 35)
  - Pictorial map of Jerusalem at this period, Circa 1985 (Box 68, Folder 36)
  - My calendars, 1985 January-April (Box 68, Folder 37)
  - Letters overseas to and from me: includes Passover letters to London friends, 1985 January-April (Box 68, Folder 38-39)
  - Lease to the house I rented, and later bought, at Rehov Nisim Behar 32, in the Nachla'ot neighborhood of Jerusalem, an old network of alleyways near the Mahane Yehuda central vegetable market: includes my hand-drawn directions to the house and a city map marked with the house's location, 1985 January (Box 68, Folder 40)